RENÉE CRUZ

(646) 704-8919 | reneebasscruz@gmail.com | Linkedin | Github | Blog | Website

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Full Stack Web Developer experienced with Ruby on Rails and JavaScript based programming. Proven track record in the music industry as a performer and a product manager. I live at the intersection of technical expertise and artistic excellence to help visionary companies build brand legacy, drive revenue and to create lasting impact.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

JavaScript (ES6+), Ruby, Rails, SQL/SQLite, Postgres, React, React Hooks, React Router, Redux, JWT Auth, Version Control (Glt/Github), Active Record, REST API, RESTful Architecture, HTML, CSS, Sinatra, MVC, OOP

TECHNICAL PROJECTS

Small Shop - Github Frontend | Github Backend | Demo | Deployed Web App

Online Shop Web App for e-commerce entrepreneurs provides secure functionality to persist user's cart and account.

- Authorized users via JSON Web Tokens and localStorage to store encrypted user information client-side for login and perisit functionality
- Built Backend API using Ruby on Rails and RESTular for user database, order logic, and perform CRUD actions
- Implemented React JS to create reusable UI components for modularity and dynamic routing using React-Router
- Utilized Redux to create a single source of truth in handling persistence of the user's account and cart logic
- Employed REST Client to query data structures from H&M Inventory API to populate items model in the backend

Horacle | Horoscope Oracle for Madlibs Astrology - <u>Github Frontend</u> | <u>Github Backend</u> | <u>Demo | Deployed Web App</u> Interactive Oracle prompt co-creates a user's future by choosing words for fun and generating a random prediction.

- Generated random Madlib data by GET request to RESTFUL Rails API backend, used Ruby & JS for logic wordbank
- Created an interactive UI using pure CSS to enable a toggle switch for the user to between light and dark mode
- Implemented Fetch to guery and retrieve data from external Horoscope & Astrology API to render daily horoscope
- Established a link to Twitter API to publish user's generated madlib horoscope on their individual Twitter account

Doggo Doption - Github Frontend | Github Backend | Demo

Pet adoption web app connects users to their new best friends and allows them virtual adoption in their secure account.

- Implemented React JS and React Router to create unique URLs & UI composed of reusable components
- Utilized JSON Web Token Authentication, BCrypt and localStorage to authenticate and authorize the user
- Fetched data from Dog CEO API and incorporated Faker Gem to generate dog data to Frontend
- Built Backend API using Ruby on Rails and designed database schema using Active Record and Postgres DB

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Accompanist, The Juilliard School, New York, NY

03/2016 - Present

- Sight-read music notation during live performances on double bass for International festival audience of thousands
- Lead bilingual masterclasses & improvised basslines in the Jazz & Black American Music idiom to instruct students

Growth Lead, Feldor Billiards Inc. DBA Fat Cat & Fat Cat Fab Lab, New York, NY

12/2008 - 03/2016

- Increased revenue from low 100K to over 5M from 2011 to 2016 by leveraging connections and marketing for live music, cultural events & educational initiatives, designed and managed website, HTML, CSS, Adobe Creative Cloud
- Established Fabrication Lab community maker space by R&D, providing access to digital fabrication tools for rapid prototyping, designed and managed website HTML, CSS, Wordpress, FTP, hosting, email marketing, social media
- Originated membership by implementing marketing strategy through community events, curriculum & classes

EDUCATION

Flatiron School, New York, New York Software Engineering Immersive

08/2019 - 12/2019

The Juilliard School, New York, New York Master of Music (MM)

08/2005 - 05/2007

The New School, New York, New York Bachelor of Fine Arts (BFA)

01/2001 - 05/2004